The goal of mathematics is not to produce mathematics papers, it's to produce some kind of understanding. Maybe some of that understanding resides in model weights. To me that's like pretty unsatisfying. Comparing anthropic with open AI, do you detect any differences in how that is similar to human reasoning? They definitely are not good at it autonomously, but with some hints you can kind of get them to do something interesting. A lot of progress in mathematics comes from like letting, you know, a thousand different flowers bloom and people pursue their own curiosity and then, you know, the
boundaries of knowledge expanded in some kind of fairly uniform way. What has been the most impressive result so far? My favorite fully autonomous result by an AI so far is the solution to the early student distance problem. There was some lemma I wanted to prove none of the frontier models could do it. So I like worked out a ton of examples on my own and I realized oh well maybe like here's some reason why it could be true. Once I had that statement the models were able to very quickly prove that sort of a better statement. How should like
The mathematics community kind of best adapt and benefit from this. AI can increasingly solve math problems that would challenge professional mathematicians. But solving a problem isn't necessarily the same thing as understanding it. In this episode, A16Z infrapartner, Leisha Lee, sits down with University of Toronto mathematician Daniel Lit to separate the headlines about AI and mathematics from what the models can actually do today.
Daniel explains why recent results have changed his views of AI, where frontier models already resemble human mathematicians. And where they still fall short, particularly when it comes to intuition, developing new theories, and even figuring out which questions are worth asking. They also explore what happens to mathematics when generating a proof becomes cheap, why academic incentives may need to change,
and how mathematicians can use AI without outsourcing the understanding that makes the work valuable in the first place. And more broadly, they ask what mathematics can teach us about working with AI as increasingly capable models move into every knowledge profession.
I am so excited to have you on Daniel. And so Daniel it is a professor of mathematics at the University of Toronto. Toronto is my hometown, so also very exciting. But the thing that is most special here is Daniel's actual practicing mathematician and in addition he's been incredibly vocal about his evolving views of AI in math. And so I feel like every, if I just don't check in with you, you know, like in two weeks something, you know, different has been revealed and then you're very kind of like.
What do you call it? You have a lot of opinions. You have a lot of opinions, exactly. So I want to get into that. So I mean, one of the things that I'm most interested in is not just like a discussion of how the capabilities of advance I feel like in math, that's definitely the headline, etc. But also you've been very thoughtful about how
practicing mathematicians should respond. And so that kind of gives us a chance and opportunity to talk about actually what is special about math. It's not just like, hey, AI has been really making progress here, but delve into what actually mathematicians do. And so maybe like with that arc in line, we can start with what has been the most impressive results so far given all the recent progress for you. And then maybe, yeah, we'll kind of take it from there.
Yeah, so okay, so there's now been a lot of results some of them produced autonomously some produced like semi autonomously some who's like the where the AI contribution is just not at all clear There's a lot of different areas. So anything I say is kind of you know I can only really comment on things that I have some expertise on so it's quite possible that if you talk to a different mathematician you'll get like different answers here So my favorite like fully autonomous result by an AI so far is the solution to the Irish unit distance problem which I think was announced in mid-May so
Oh, that's what I liked about that is it seemed to me that like it was in some ways a little bit creative. So I think some of the results we've seen have had kind of the flavor of you kind of take some known techniques and apply them in maybe a clever way or you know, they've kind of been some kind of results I would characterize as like last mile, like where some recent work was done, like quite deep work done by a group of human mathematicians. And then the AI took the final step.
But yeah, with this sort of distance problem, I think it was something where the result was a little unexpected. So first of all, my sense was that people working in the area thought it was true and then there was a counter example found. But then also it brought in some techniques from another area. I think those techniques were not especially deeper new. There were sort of classical ideas from the 60s, but they were new to this area of studying point configurations in the plane.
And so that was pretty cool. And then afterwards we got to see like it was kind of fruitful. So a bunch of mathematicians took those ideas and used them to find counter examples to a bunch of other interesting open questions. So for example, like the song product conjecture over the real numbers. So that's what at least what way I like to think about how cool. Yeah. So it is like you look at it post hoc and you see like, oh, well, we're whatever new ideas that were introduced if any like kind of useful to do other things that they improve our understanding of something. And I think that's maybe so far the main example.
I know of a result of that form. Yeah, I think it's really meaningful that you're commenting on this because that result came out to your point in May and there's been so many headlines so far and it's kind of probably hard for somebody who's not a practicing mathematician to appreciate the differences in these headlines.
you kind of already started laying out sort of a taxonomy of like what is different in that proof. And so it'd be kind of interesting maybe to use that as kind of both an excuse to talk about where you sense the model differences are and what like mathematicians actually do. So in this case, I mean the most kind of maybe naive understanding of what mathematicians do is that we're pushing around symbols in a logical manner. And this is why RL is so successful at this because you can kind of both verify it.
somewhat cheaply compared to other domains and then also because the rules are quite legible and so you can kind of like if you're superhuman at that you might be good at math. But I think that of course betrays most of actually what is interesting about mathematics which is perhaps I think you said this as well but I think anybody who's tried to do math is sort of like it's about the understanding and getting at truth, remaining confused and developing intuitions and I mean the tool to do that stuff is of course in having really
strong abilities to push out logical implications. But maybe if you can kind of speak to like when you say it's most impressive and creative like decoupling just the inhumane maybe feats of just like logical implication from like where is it being creative? What is it helping engender in terms of like mathematical activity as well?
Yeah, okay. So first of all, I mean you have characterized it as like inhuman in some way I actually think the argument was very human. I love to go to the opening I like released some chain of thought Yeah, it was very recognizable was like if I tried to imagine like my chain of thought Yeah, trying to solve a problem like it might look kind of like that
Yeah. We haven't seen the raw chain of thought so maybe that would... Maybe they cleansed it a little bit, yeah. Yeah, or maybe the model like to swirl on the middle of the chain of thought and clean that up or something would know. But at least the summary seems pretty reasonable. And I would say that's actually like kind of typical of most of the results that I've studied. Like they don't seem inhuman at all. They seem absolutely like something a human mathematician could produce.
And they're like typically understandable if not so well written. If you just look at problem output, it's not like there's some move 37 or whatever. It's like a human mathematician doing math. It's like a human mathematician doing certain types of math. So like they're definitely like the models are still like not very good at some math, math, math, and other activities. And here I don't mean like by field, but just like certain things you do when you try to solve a problem, the models don't seem to be doing, but certain things they're very good at.
The ways they might be a little bit un-inhuman is like they don't get tired, they know a lot, but if you actually just read the final output it doesn't seem kind of inhuman. It's interesting because, I mean, obviously we can't get too much information from the labs who are producing these models of why, of what the training recipes are, or how they're kind of advancing in reasoning. But at least one of the things we do know, and I think kind of open AI spearheaded this, is it's like reasoning in natural language is actually what they happen to scale up and it's not actually pushing a lot of...
a lean verified proofs as like the training corpus and that's kind of amazing. On another side, what's kind of interesting is it's not clear that a lot of the mathematical training data, if they use that to a large extent at all, is
reflective of how mathematicians think, if that's fair, because a lot of it is not legible as traces, right? Like most of the papers are crisp and polished. The textbooks certainly just show very little motivation of how something is developed, which is why it's usually easier to follow research direction by actually talking to the researchers and how they're thinking about it.
I'm kind of curious before maybe even going to the taxonomy as an excuse, like when you're examining these models and their results comparing anthropic with open AI, do you detect any differences in how that is similar to human reasoning? And then also if you have any comments on like insights on perhaps why natural language scales so well that way.
Even though it's okay. So first of all, I really like your point by the way that they're mostly doing natural language reasoning rather than lean like I think that that suggests to me that like these you hear a lot of people say like math is a verifiable domain like that explains the progress or like my sense is that because they're primarily scaling informal reasoning like probably the techniques are done I generalized other domains pretty well That's just my guess. Okay. You asked a little bit about Claude versus check APT my sense is that they're
pretty similar in terms of capabilities. I've played around a lot more with ChetGBT than Claude Fable. But it seems like there's a lot of cases where open AI will drop a solution to some problem and anthropics will say, oh, you know, we also do. It actually seems like they're solving a very similar collection of problems. And it's like kind of a relatively small portion of what human mathematicians do.
So yeah, one thing that is interesting is like we see the solutions have a certain flavor, right? Like they'll be things that this isn't surprising. Like they'll be things that rely on the model strengths, like their ability to ground out a long computation or pull together kind of technical ideas from many areas or like maybe many papers that you know, even my mathematician might not have read it, but they're not like they seem like weaker and things like intuition or like having some big picture point of view. Like a lot of what I do as a mathematician is like I have some kind of philosophy that's like very non-rigorous.
Like maybe I think this thing is kind of analogous to this thing. And then like a lot of what I'm working out is like figuring out how to make that precise and like, you know, trying to measure the extent to which I've succeeded in understanding that by like, can I solve a problem or whatever? Or like, can I find an interesting phenomenon which I don't understand and now I understand it. And like so far, I haven't, you know, you can say even the best results, the models are perusing. You don't see that much of this kind of reasoning. It's more like,
they're very, very good at applying some known techniques, which is to be clear, that's like a very powerful thing to do to be very good at applying like all known techniques. There are mathematicians who have had great careers doing very high quality work with that flavor. And I think a lot of what the models are producing is high quality in that way, but it's like some kind of fairly narrow band of what mathematicians care about. So far, I do think there's like signs of both, you know, all the frontier models
starting to be able to do more fuzzy things. So like I've tried to get both both fable and chat GPT 5.6 all I guess to do some kind of theory building and it's like they definitely are not good at it autonomously at least with like whatever scaffolding I've set up but with some hints you can kind of get them to do something interesting. You know when you do when you give the models hints it's always a little hard to tell like
what part is from the model and what part is from you, but my experience is that like if they can do it with like 100 bits of hints or whatever in six months, maybe they can do it without hints. I do think there's signs that they're also kind of somehow picking up some of this like implicit and unwritten mathematical knowledge. Okay. I would love to go into the intuition part and where it sucks at.
to put it in a very basic way, but you actually mentioned a small detail which is that you know from the public you've gleaned that anthropic and open air probably neck and neck but you personally are using a lot more Chatchi P.T. like why is that? Or five plus six? Well, I don't know. I think it's just in our show. Pretty sure of habit. One thing is that Chatchi P.T. got better at math earlier.
Like for a long time, the cloud models were just like not useful for research math. And I think maybe around OPIS 4.5 or OPIS 4.6, they're like more or less caught up. But some experimentations, they're just to me, they're pretty neck and neck. And so for my own work, except when I'm just experimenting, I must have just stick with one. Yeah. As people outside of labs like us, it's really interesting just to compare how they differ on the frontier.
you know, to your point, it might be a little bit of momentum. I do think that, at least from my anecdotal experience, 5.6 has been like a lot more clear in exposition. And it just like, it's a little bit, and this might not be true. I mean, obviously the models are just incredibly jagged at the frontier. But like, it's in the explanations of results to me, I always find that 5.6 is giving,
more accurate theory of mind of what it assumes I know and don't know. Whereas fable might be explaining something very trivial, but then just like jump at like well, you know, obviously you should know these things and yeah, I find they're both pretty bad at theory of thought.
Okay, great. So then seeing from your eyes, you're probably asking much deeper questions. Okay, so the thread that I really wanted to pull on was when you're talking about the models maybe starting to get better intuitions or even theory building. So maybe before we even dive into that, it would be useful to kind of talk through like what is your primary activity as a mathematician, especially in your area of like algebraic geometry.
Probably has a very different flavor than a combinatorialist or you know some other areas So if you can give a little maybe brief lay of the land and then kind of explain what your what your math Mathematical activity was pre AI and then maybe how it's kind of like changing with AI Yeah, so so I think there are a lot of different kinds of mathematicians. There's like a lot of different You know spectra on which one can put a mathematician So Definitely a lot of mathematicians like solving open problems
And then I think I'm one of those like I like to solve an open problem That's I think of myself as a problem solver as opposed to like one you know one other taxonomy you could you could have is a problem solver versus a theory builder At least for me the point of an open problem is it's like supposed to measure your failure to understand something so it's kind of like a benchmark Right like, you know
One problem I really like is the growth in decaps, de-carpeture, whatever that is, it measures something about our failure to understand differential equations. So it's like there's some very basic object we would like to understand. If we can't answer this conjecture, we know we don't understand it. Okay, so in practice, how do you get a problem which is supposed to be measuring something you don't understand? Well, of course, you try to understand the thing better. And in practice, what that means is like,
Well, you try to find the smallest situation where you can't understand something and f**k fiddle with it and then you stare at like what once you win you stare at like what you developed to win and try to turn that into some theory So that's one thing you might do you might try to like solve a problem and in so doing develop some kind of new understanding of the situation You might also just like have some feeling that like this thing is related to this other thing
And you might start building a table, let go of this property a is related to property a prime, property b is related to property b prime and so on and so forth. So for example, in my work, a lot of it is motivated by some analogy between the comology of algebraic varieties and representations of fundamental groups. So that's some fancy stuff. But it's just that this analogy is very fruitful and really any phenomenon that appears on one side, you can find an analog on the other side.
And so trying to realize that dream has led to a lot of beautiful mathematics blessed like 30 or 40 years by people like Carlos Simpson and to Karl Marchesuki and others. And so here it's really just like someone noticed like here's an analogy and then that analogy has like led to a huge amount of developments. There's not really like an open problem at the end, although of course like as you develop this, you come up with lots of open problems. There's just like a philosophy.
that you're trying to realize. And that philosophy is like super not rare essentially. It's not like symbol pushing it all. Yeah, so that's another kind of activity that I like. Yeah, beyond that, a lot of what you do when you try to, a lot of the activities, you're actually trying to figure out what the right question is even.
Like here you have some object, you feel like you don't understand it, and like figuring out what you don't know is like actually a very challenging thing to do. So, you know, there's like a list of, you know, you can go online and list open conjectures or whatever. And this doesn't really capture in a lot of ways what we don't know. Like often finding the conjecture is like really, really hard. So I know a good example of this is like the Bershwin-Schwinn-Nerchendier conjecture, which is one of plenty of problems.
is this like beautiful relationship between L functions of elliptic curves and the set of solutions to the corresponding equations with a rank of the group of solutions, what that means. It was discovered by like, it was like the first big data conjecture. So Bershwin-Sönert and Dyer had like found all these statistics all elliptic curves in the 60s, like it was one of the first ever computer aided bits of mathematics. And they like graphed these statistics and they noticed that
The slope of some line on the graph was related to some other algebraic invariant they knew, and that was the source of this conductor. So a lot of the time you're just working at examples and you're doing kind of science. You run an experiment and you try to figure out an explanation for that experiment. And so I think going back to AI, I think these are things where AI seems so far to help a lot more in some things than other things. So I think the more vague
a phenomenon is, or the less you have a precise question in mind, the less useful it happens to be. And so you were asking how I use it in my daily life. Actually, what I've found is that the projects that I have that predate AI, like the projects I've been thinking about for three or four or five years,
It's just not that useful. Like it's primarily kind of a substitute for Google or something like I might use it to like learn about some related topic or like something where I would have earlier Googled something and then like read a paper like maybe I'll discuss it with AI instead. So it saves some time for sure. It's like not really doing deep intellectual work for me. But then, you know, because I, you know, I'm now like, well, I suck at coding. And so now I know, you know, my good friend who's
really good at coding and now I have all these coding projects. Because like suddenly, if I had a question where coding would have been really useful, I would have procrastinated on it for six months until I... Tireless page to a student. Exactly. So yeah, now I've picked up all these projects where yeah, coding is really useful. Like the models are like very good for kind of massively parallel things. Like if you want to find an example of something, you can just ask it to find, you know, work through a thousand examples in parallel or it would be 10 examples at a time.
you know, tend to be sub-agents and like that's really useful. But these are like kind of different activities which are like, I don't know, on top of what I was doing before. I'd love to dig in. Yeah, go on. Yeah, sorry, because you were mentioning, you know, there's projects that you've been working on for like three, four, five years and I don't know if it's correct to say like those are more of the theory building aspect of it because you did characterize yourself as like an open problem solver or like what is the thing that is, because like the deep thinking part, maybe, maybe like, you know,
kind of for this audience, it might also be useful to kind of say or explain, you know, most of pure math is it's not like it's being motivated.
by, nothing on applied math, but applied math is like at least there's some external motivation for why a certain formal structure might be interesting to study, whereas this one it's like purely, it seems almost sociological and to some extent I think like Thurston made some comment or a point about this in the 70s that it is a sociological phenomenon, more and more mathematicians start examining something, then you'll maybe you know converge on some interesting structures, but it's just like it's not, there's some
reason why people would prefer to study something where they think it's beautiful. Like what is it that drives maybe you in particular and then maybe you can make a more general comment about the profession? Yeah, I mean, so definitely some people are like motivated by like beauty or kind of aesthetic considerations. I'd try not to be motivated by that. Oh, that's quite a bit. Yeah, I think that's a bad way. Yeah. Like, well, one thing, like that sort of limits you, right? Like one thing, kind of a failure mode I see among young mathematicians sometimes is like,
you have something and you kind of think you know how to prove it and then like the proof feels really ugly and you decide but like okay I mean what if you're wrong it's not ugly like why limit yourself to this audience like what is ugly because I have an information of what's ugly but like what is that for kind of spelling out I don't really know I don't really have aesthetic feelings but people
People sometimes feel this way. Maybe it involves a lot of grinding, so it's not a calculation that's not illuminating. Exactly. But you should win by any means necessary, in my opinion. I like to think of what I'm doing, doing physics except with concepts. So instead of beauty, I try to think about maybe what is kind of fundamental, what's going to open up further understanding most. Am I introducing a new idea that will be broadly useful to understand this object?
I guess, you know, in some sense there's like some aesthetic consideration there, but it's I try to I think the orientation of like trying to do good science rather than trying to do art. Yeah, I prefer but there's a huge even there's a huge variety of Opinions here and like lots of mathematicians think of themselves as being like closer to poets or something Yeah, what I do think is broadly true is that like progress comes from people like it seems to come in mathematics from people sort of pursuing their personal curiosity
And that it's sort of been crucial historically that there's like a lot of different people with different views of what's interesting and then the frontier of knowledge expands and expands and then suddenly you know you have these opportunistic situations where a new idea has been introduced and you can now find you now can suddenly like cascade through a bunch of other things that we didn't understand before. Yeah, I mean so then going back to the three four five year problems and where are the models sort of not useful?
kind of ask it another way. Like when you're doing the deep thinking, like is it just that it's just not clear that you formulated as a problem and it's more that you're thinking about these, like what are the fundamental kind of physics of, you know. So in some cases, I mean, the, some cases there is like a well stated problem here. You know, I said I've been thinking about things for seven, you know, maybe 10 years now at this point for certain problems. Sometimes there is just like a conjecture.
that I would like to prove that is there. I think one reason the models might not be useful for some of these things is like the conductors are true. So like, I think that certain, for example, on this unit distance problem, like the general belief in the community was that it was true and then it turned out to be false. And so what that means is that there's like a specific construction you can do to refute it.
On the other hand, I think a lot of the things I think about like, I don't know, okay, maybe I'm about to, you know, this one will come up with this Andrews Alcult, the Peacovercher conjecture room on hypothesis tomorrow and like, I'll look like a fool. But in general, like these conjectures fit into some very broad theoretical framework, which means that, look, we actually have a lot of evidence that they're true. And so, you know, yeah, so that's part of it. Like there's not like a construction you can do to refute it. You need to somehow
kind of, you know, this, we have this giant framework where certain, certain pieces of it are only conjectured, well, and you probably need to resolve some of those conjectures to win. We also have like a pretty good sense, I think, that like very serious new ideas are needed to resolve those conjectures. So like, of course you can't be sure, like maybe there's some very clever construction that will let you, I don't know, avoid having a big new idea. I don't know.
maybe it's quite possible we'll find this out. But my sense is that for at least a lot of the things I've been thinking about, they're just not accessible to applying known techniques in a very technically strong way. So you need to develop a new technique. Just to be clear, I'm not saying the models won't be able to do this. It's just like so far they seem not to. Actually, that's exactly the point that I wanted to delve into because it's some
You know to point to your point it's like okay We can try to try to calibrate in forecast like why they would get better at this but it is true like you know that just providing construction for a counter example They seem to be strong on if you have to start developing either new theory or to your point techniques machinery to solve to prove why conjecture is true
it struggles more and it's probably because a lot of what it's drawing on is also just like techniques that have happened in other areas and they're porting it over and to your point that's why maybe the unit distance problem was such a more creative result because it was maybe doing more of that on its own. I was like from another at least it was like drawing in something. Yeah it was. Exactly, exactly and so like maybe then to kind of ask the question it's not that because now we're like okay fine AI is getting so good so fast we can't count it out but like why what do you think it has to
Yeah, I guess it's it's you're spelling out what it has to get better at but maybe some more kind of feelings on like why it's kind of particularly hard to then develop that new theory and technology. That's a good question. I think you just need a different like my my guess actually is it's probably totally doable. It just hasn't been done yet. Like maybe you just need a different RL environment. I don't know. Yeah, so I mean at this point my expectation is just like that the trajectory will continue upwards. I'm not a skeptic of continued capabilities growth.
But yeah, I think what is definitely true is that the skill of developing a theory or building your understanding of some poorly understood object is a fuzzier one. So it might be harder. I guess you can tell it, develop your understanding of Zeta functions. And then once it proves through your hypothesis, you give it a reward. But it's kind of harder, I think, to come up with some intermediate things that you reward.
Yeah, that said, I do think mathematics as a whole provides a lot of conjectures of varying levels of difficulty. So maybe this explains why there seems to be a little bit of progress in these areas. Presumably they are trying to get it to solve lots of problems and solve those problems to develop at least some of the skills of theory building. Humans are able to develop these skills.
I guess sometimes they get rewards from their PhD advisors and their advisors says, oh, that's a good idea or something based on some element of human taste or whatever. And that might be something one can do too. But yeah, my expectation is that just look as part of continued capabilities growth, we'll see growth in these areas too. Yeah, and I like the framing where you're sort of casting these increasingly difficult conjectures as a form of curricula for both humans and of course AI.
It, you know, maybe kind of getting a little bit too philosophical for some people's taste. It's like it gets at the question of like, why are we particularly good or maybe particularly bad at math too? Because it's, you know, what is it that we're either struggling to do or some people are particularly good at when you develop new theory? Because it's not, again, it's like not really...
Or maybe it's related to like why can we formulate good structures for physics as well? It's just like it's not obvious all parts of the world are kind of understandable and legible that way but some parts are and therefore we try to do it because there's maybe compressive pressures on our you know our minds because we need to we can't understand anything beyond you know compressing stuff more finely. I don't know if that's also like the correct
interpretation of like, yeah. I'm a little bit skeptical as like compression as a metric of interest, but it's definitely like as a anthropological reason for like why we do a certain theory of building ice. I think it's true. And in fact, I think it's like kind of like our inability to just grind is kind of important to our ability to make discoveries. So I'm just like as an example, so I have one paper out so far where the models were kind of useful. So they like proved a couple of us.
So this is some situation where we had to kind of prove in the main result and then there were like some lemmas I was unhappy with, like they seem not to be optimal and so I like worked with, actually this was with Jammai Deepthink, which at the time was also on the frontier, no longer. I kind of worked with it to improve the lemmas. And so what happened here was there was some lemma I wanted to prove and the models couldn't do it. So none of the frontier models could do it.
And so I worked out a ton of examples on my own and I realized, oh well maybe here's some reason why it could be true. So I had a better statement of the line. And then, okay once I had that statement, okay probably I could have done it pretty fast but also the models were able to very quickly prove that sort of better statement.
So like our inability to prove it like led to an improvement in the result. Okay, now you can take the original Lemai head that the models weren't able to prove, put it into chat GP5.6 Pro and it will output like the worst proof you've ever seen like 10 pages of like just brutal calculation with no insight whatsoever. And so okay, this would have been a perfectly un-proof, but it would not have led to this discovery of like a, I think a kind of beautiful conceptual explanation for why this thing, we discovered what's true. So like we found a better proof because we couldn't do
I mean, okay, I say we couldn't do with the huck, I should look what actually happened. And here I understand that I'm being hypocritical about my complaints about ugly proofs before. It's like, I realized like this horrible grind proof would work. I like could not bring myself to do it. And so I like to turn other argument.
And so I mean it's not, yeah, it's but new and out the models can do us for very long and technical calculation is pretty reliably. Yeah, well, I mean, I don't know. I think I understand why you're saying it's like don't you know, just shy away from trying to prove something just because it seems that way because it's like you have to take the first step, right? And eventually you all try to work towards insight and so, you know, you might be shy about admitting it, but it is still maybe driven by whether it's like
Aesthetics or just like pure, you know, like I want to understand and if understanding just means it's a little bit simpler or you know more compressed than I've gotten understanding I mean, that's just like a deep philosophical question too is like what it is right like I mean, of course any You know, there's a reason we do informal mathematics rather than like writing out long informal strings of symbols of CFC or whatever Yeah, you know besides like somehow we're trying to put it in a way where we are actually getting some non rigorous understanding now. Yeah, I mean I think somehow
Yeah, and even how that even relates to why it helps. And again, is it because of our inability to grind or is it because if we are pushing towards something that's more compressive, it also hopefully also ascends on the does it help?
understand other fields as well. And it's just, it is somewhat magical that when we try to optimize for the both, that it tends to coincide. I don't know actually, you know, if that's a fair, it's actually a quantitative statement. But like why, you know, that is, is kind of magical. It's at least sometimes true. Yeah, exactly. Or, you know, we certainly bias towards the cases in which it is. That's why we call that a good theory to build. But it's, yeah, it's very much, I think, you know,
It's like this is what we can study and understand and therefore it's also very convenient that it was rich in kind of mathematical results there. Yeah, I mean, okay, so I think there's two things that we can like, you know, pull on, which is like what given you've seated that, or not seated, but you've
I believe that mathematical ability of AI is going to continue advancing. It can do some of the things that you're doing nowadays. How should the mathematics community best adapt and benefit from this? I mean, as a just kind of saying, as somebody who doesn't have the time to kind of practice mathematics anymore, this is kind of very great because I can maybe dabble more. There's a lot of results that can come out. But I can also see where you've made
the more precise point of we can not motivate the right kind of behavior of understanding and development. And so we'd love to kind of hear more about your views there. Yeah, so okay, so first of all, like it is clearly really exciting, like that there are increasingly models that are like producing high-quality results. At least some high-quality results, also a lot of stuff. Yeah, some good stuff. And so, you know, as the models get
really capable, you know, my hope is that they will answer a lot of the questions that I've been like, you know, kept up at night thinking about, I'm like, I'll get to learn the answers. I think that's really exciting. And, you know, a lot of people got into math, like largely because they enjoyed learning math.
Right, like the first thing to do as a math student is you learn stuff that other people did and you do that for like 20 years before you start doing it. Oh, maybe not quite 20 years. 15 years. If you're lucky, 20 years. Yeah, you started early. Yeah. Yeah. So that said, the goal of mathematics is not to produce mathematics papers. It's to produce some kind of understanding.
So maybe, okay, maybe that some of that understanding resides in model weights or something. To me, that's like pretty unsatisfying. Like my own, you know, my motivation for doing mathematics is like, I would like to satisfy my own personal curiosity. I think people should be have the capability to do that. And like that requires a pretty substantial apparatus. Like it's like simply not the case that you can like study the questions I think are fundamental unless you've invested a huge amount of time and effort.
kind of getting to the point where you can meaningfully do so. And then moreover, like that, you know, even the people, like, you know, you have the small group of people doing like fancy research math on the frontier or whatever, that relies on like a huge apparatus of like, you know, thousands and millions or billions of people who are trying to learn to think mathematically, like you need an entire mathematical community to support a small group of people who are on the frontier, like you just without the pipeline, the pipeline doesn't exist.
So if you think that's important like development of human capital that can like meaningfully engage with frontier mathematics I think that you know you still have to incentivize those people to actually invest their time and effort getting to the point where they can engage and then do so in a high quality meaningful way. So right now I think like the existing incentives structures for math research do not do not encourage people to do that. So you know right now if you're like a postdoc on the market you want to get a job
maybe for the next couple years before the community adapts, the best way to do that is like you want to produce a lot of papers which may be proof, you know, old conjectures or whatever and you can do that by playing the slot machine until the model pre-s is a hopefully correct proof of such result. So you don't even have to pick the the the the term in advance. So like here's an experiment you can do. You can take codecs. You can say go online and find five recent conjectures in algebraic geometry and prove them.
And okay, I've run this experiment and with some back and forth, I was able to, you know, in an hour get like three, you know, quite bad papers, but correct papers, which okay, now sitting on my hard drive waiting for me to email the relevant people, but this is not a good use of my time to invest results. But yeah, you definitely see people doing this. So there's been a huge uptick in post to archive, mostly not very interesting. Some of it is interesting.
But a lot of it is kind of clearly low quality even if in so far as the... Even if the result is something that would have been kind of highly rewarded a year ago, just like there's sort of no evidence that a human being is actually engaged with it. Like there's no development of human capital or understanding.
like sometimes, you know, we've seen examples where like three or four or five papers with the exact same proof of the exact same theorem out and within a couple days of each other, which is clearly, you know, some situation where someone's playing the slot machine, yeah, check GPT is kind of consistently finding the same. That's also interesting. It's like not it's kind of mode collapsed on like certain pads of reasoning. Yeah. Yeah. And I think it's like not obvious that this problem goes away as the models get better. Like maybe it does, but maybe it doesn't. Like I think
A lot of what I was saying earlier is that a lot of progress in mathematics comes from like letting you know a thousand different flowers bloom and people yeah pursue their own curiosity and then you know the boundaries of knowledge expand in some kind of fairly hopefully fairly uniform way and look it's really high-dimensional space of mathematics and Then like opportunistically you you suddenly get some applications or like as is told questions we found and it's like not clear to me that if if you know
we can subordinate mathematical exploration to what the model want to pursue, like if what you're getting is like one mathematician duplicated a thousand times, or like actually a million different mathematicians doing a million different things. Yeah, I think actually that's pretty, I mean aside from like, okay math has to adapt by changing set of structures, I think this is actually a pretty, maybe...
dangerous or something that the labs have to pay attention to because you know on one side what's been successful for them is that this emergent reasoning capabilities obviously incredibly powerful and we've been I mean it's just created a lot of like great PR headlines but you know to your point and also like where I might
interest tend to is that like human mathematicians, they are coming from all sorts of weird intuitions that like you know and that is why you end up developing you know to your point the frontier that is so diverse that you actually can draw from and then be able to connect and produce a lot more and so it if it's true that most of these like
proofs that are being pushed out by the labs are converging on very similar things because they are technically drawing on the same body of literature and that's where they're strong at now. It's not clear that, I mean one, where are they developing their intuitions? It's from practicing mathematicians. It's not clear whether that other emergent, stronger, diverse intuition might be coming from. It might come, but I don't have a good...
Theory for where it comes from and it's also just not clear that you know just with like test time compute and various post training Scaling that you can even I mean it's a huge debate whether you could be introduced new capabilities And it's like precisely I think you should be studied in the math context because like where it's good at and where it fails And where human mathematicians are good or is exactly a very kind of like precise Question to study it on So this is like a long way of saying that I
It isn't clear to me that we'll maybe produce, if we don't incentivize enough people to interact with it, maybe unlike other domains, it might not actually continue producing a superior result without human aid. Yeah. Let me actually push a bit further even. So like let's suppose the models become like really robustly superhuman, like even like we're not even adding like meaningful cognitive literacy. Okay. I claim like still actually we'd be still one.
Okay great. So many mathematicians. Yeah. So right, so why? So like it's because the, you know, there's like a, it's like there's a question on how we've, we're designing society, right? Like you maybe the optimal situation is like you have the models doing all sorts of math research and like that leads to very, you know, in this like highly, you know.
whatever, non-uniform diverse way, like maybe you don't need humans to add that kind of diversity. So like maybe that's the optimal thing to do. And like in the end that leads to lots of applications and lots of improved understanding and so on. It's like despite something being optimal doesn't mean you do it, right? Like there's no reason to think that, you know, if we hand over control of whatever, after research to the models and just let them do their own thing, that it will do the optimal thing.
And in fact, if we kind of instrumentalize what we want them to do, like we want to say, like, oh, make our life better or whatever, it might not be the case that what they decide to do that is pursue a wide variety of interesting research. They might just try to take the direct path. We don't know what's going to happen. So I don't know, if you believe that there is any value in sort of this broad-based,
fundamental research, which I do look, I think that's one of the most valuable things humans or whatever the models can be doing. I think the easiest way to guarantee it happens is to keep a community with broad interests, pushing the models to do it, helping us to design a society where that's what we're pushing for. I think at least, my hopeful vision for the future is that humans are not totally disempowered, we have control over where we're going. And if that's the case, what we end up doing,
is going to be driven by human interests. And so you want to have people who have lots of different interests and also the capabilities to actually pursue them. Which you want people who are like smart and engaged and like, you know, well, can do not just like mathematical thinking, but all sorts of thinking. Yeah, yeah. I mean, yeah, a great fear is like as AI advances, we don't develop the right ergonomic kind of interfaces to actually encourage us to also be good, continue to be good thinkers. And it's so easy to kind of
relinquish that because you just awful and the models aren't even good at that level of like, you know thinking where it's like the top level structure but despite that it's it's so easy to and so especially for math I mean just like you know another selfish reason is if you kind of math max you know I think it's actually great pedagogical excuse to actually get
just really rigorous at thinking about various things. I mean, this is not why mathematicians do it, but as just somebody who likes part of what I do. Okay, great. Because it was kind of, you know, I thought it just really helped give me a very...
good framework to think about many things, not just mathematics. And as somebody who's also now a parent of a two-year-old, I kind of think about this a lot too. It's not about kind of grinding, even though whatever, it's still good, but not to shit on grinding too much. But just hearing, I used to collaborate a bunch with some Hungarian mathematicians, Balazssegadi among them, and I just heard that...
In in Budapest, they would just teach group theory when you're in primary school and like, well, we should definitely do that. We should continue doing that. Now that AI is so good at, you know, somewhat good at explaining, but it's far more accessible. We should actually, you know, probably proliferate that even more. And so maybe that helps with bringing more people to the frontier rather than, you know, just. Yeah. I mean, this is something I'm concerned about, right? Of course, I mostly talk about math because that's like where I live. But like, I think, you know, one nice thing about thinking about this is
We're one of the first professions to have a significant impact of high quality models, although I think maybe we're one of the first professions to happen to the public. But my sense is that there are plenty of professions that are heavily impacted. Coding. Coding. But also just like, I mean, I think that anything you do at a computer, like probably a huge amount is being done by the models at this point. But I'm like, there's not having a public reckoning about it.
because math capabilities are useful for the labs to talk about, I think, more publicly than everyone else. But yeah, I think one reason to try to maintain human capital in this area is just it's a model for all professions. Presumably we still want people who are like, meaningfully engaging with the world and like experts and have like talents and trained skills and so on.
Yeah, so it's actually very convenient that the math profession is so inclined with education here because I think we're also seeing like, you know, some amount of challenges, you know, among college and like secondary education coming from the ITU. So as you said, I mean, it's also an amazing tool to learn.
Yeah. People have, I've heard people start talking about a bimodal distribution in their classes where there's some people who are really like figuring out how to take advantage of neutrals and other people who are just like letting them do their homework and then bomb you with anything else.
Unfortunately, I don't think that adapts fast enough, but it's like we definitely want to be living in a world where we're producing better thinkers. I think it's just, you know, even if we talk about just the pure kind of optimization game, I think that's better for us. So, but as, you know, just like a human being, I'm like, that would be pretty.
inconvenient if we became worse thinkers just as AI ascends and it's too easy to let that happen. So we should kind of be thinking hard on how to actually take advantage of this and harness it for our own improvement. Right. Yeah, I think it's like it's sort of interesting to observe like the models at their current level capabilities let you do a lot more. They let you do a lot of things you wouldn't have done more cheaply than you know cheaply enough to do them now.
But it's not clear to me that like in many cases they're actually improving the quality of outputs. Yeah, and I think this is common like you have a new technology that's doing something a little bit worse than was previously done but much cheaper. And so you get a lot of suddenly a lot of like low quality outputs that are displacing previous high quality outputs. But I think it's possible to use the tools in a way that actually like improves, you know, the quality of among, among every dimension it just refers requires some thoughtfulness and some some redesign of institutions should actually incentivize that. Yeah.
Well, hopefully capitalism works there. I do feel like the the most high value things do require people to use it effectively. And right now the models are not good enough without like the human experts to actually participate. But to your point, there's a vast majority of maybe like more junior and entry level. And if you know it's it's harder for for those rules to adapt as well. And so the thing that would be a mistake is to
use the AI models in a way that doesn't.
Basically, you need to be ascending and using the models to deepen your understanding. And it's so easy for human nature just to be lazy. And you have to resist that because that is the moment that you will kind of lose basically. And so you kind of forgive the very competitive language, but it really is like, it's just so easy to relinquish the thinking to the models. The models can't really think. And so as things are ascending so fast, it's like critical that you continue developing those.
facilities and actually leverage it to improve those facilities rather than relinquish. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, one thing I think has been nice about, you know, sort of this vast increase in like semi-expert detention or like model attention on math problems is like now there's been, you know, okay, I've been complaining about slot papers or whatever, like, you know, people who are not.
producing really high quality stuff, often that's actually coming from professionals. Like it's not saying like, you know, the people who, you know, like within academic mathematics, there are incentives to produce like a lot of stuff and that's, you know.
that's one place to stop coming from. So there's definitely also like stop coming from non-experts, but that I kind of actually don't see as a net negative. Like, okay, there's a lot of, now there's a lot of like documents on the internet one might have to come through to figure out if a problem has been solved or not. But to me it seems like just the fact that there's lots of people excited about math is like kind of a positive. So that's like a nice thing. I totally agree. I don't think that's a talk to me. They're not even kind of positive, obviously.
Yeah, yeah, no, exactly. It's like suddenly there's a spotlight on it and I can nerd out about math more. I was actually kind of curious if you've any comments on the, I guess this is another constructive result, but the elliptic curve of rank 30, that just came out yesterday. So if that... That's right. Yeah, yeah. We don't have any details about it yet. I know, there's rumors that it's... Yeah, we don't know how it... I mean, so it's due to...
I guess Claude Fable prompted by Levent Alpoge and a collaborator whose name I unfortunately forget. Maybe you can add it in post. I just know the Twitter handle. Yeah, we can add it. So a lot of these nice recent results have come from Levent with unclear amounts of autonomy. So my sense is that some of them are semi-autonomous rather than fully-autonomous. With this, we don't know anything about the methods.
So yeah, this is a fun construction. Without knowing about the methods, it's very hard to say how significant it is. What I would say is that if you want to understand, kind of historically, how such results have been proved, or sorry, have been understood by the community, they're like cool, but I wouldn't say they're like a big deal. So like the typical place to result like this might go is like someone's website of records.
It's on Annal's level result. Yeah, it's not an Annal's but that said it's cool and it's like a make you know it definitely there were a few very very or are a few very very talented mathematicians who like these kinds of questions and know Malchies being maybe the most famous example so Alchies and Clegg Spoon are the ones who kind of have been pushing this record for a while and they recently found a rank 29 example. One up. So those are mathematicians.
And I think you know people like it and it's cool now that the models can do this sort of thing But yeah, it's very you know one thing I always say about a model result is like you cannot Evaluate it except in retrospect and like this is also true of human mathematics like yeah sometimes a problem We thought was really important or would require really neat deep new ideas does not and sometimes it does and you can't really know an advance So it's always exciting when a problem like that gets solved But then like to figure out how significant is you stop to look and like well event and Claude
And I think Ava Howell, maybe since the collaborator, had not yet told us how they did it. Have they been mostly more secretive? I think they released some traces of stuff. Yeah, so for this one, I think they haven't yet, unless I missed it. Levent likes to tweet out his results. But yeah, he has been slowly releasing some kind of PDF write-ups too. I think he's just having fun on the internet. Yeah, yeah.
It reminds me of when you're saying you have to evaluate how the results came. So I had Mark, Selkie, and Metab, Swani on from OpenAI recently. And they were saying how it's kind of been the most charming or delightful is just that the proofs have been relatively short. They're not like 200 page and maybe corresponding to your grinding point as well. But maybe this is kind of optimized for in retrospect.
It was picked that it was short or maybe do you find that on average? stuff that you throw at GPT, you know Saul or fable tends to be shorter and more legible to the human or versus it might just go haywire and Just grind it out. Yeah, so so I mean I think it is nice that will sometimes produce short clover proofs Yeah, that's of course everyone likes a short clover proof. I think my sense is that
the reason they're not producing long complicated proofs is that they cannot. Just like that the ability to check correctness is not yet there. So, I mean even actually if you ask the models to produce short proof, you can then often ask them to just ask is that correct? And they will often say no. So like they're much more reliable than they were six months ago for sure. But like it's still,
they will still sometimes produce things that are just wrong and they know they're wrong. I think the problem with producing a very long thing is they might not know they're wrong. But I wonder if presumably internally OpenAI and Anthropics have probably solved a lot more problems than they've released, and I imagine quite a few of them are just not sure if they're true. So for example, with this recent list of 10 problems released by OpenAI, those were all formalized in Lean.
which is of course a very good evidence that they're true. I have no doubt that there were a lot more that they could not formalize in Lee. Like, yeah, because the prerequisite options have not been put into mass Philippia, for example. There were probably more that were longer, which also makes it challenging to check. So yeah, this is my guess. And we do actually see very long, I generated proofs on the archive. So for example, someone recently posted.
acclaimed proof of resolution of singularities and positive characteristics which is 800 AI generated pages. It's definitely, I mean, I'm sorry, I haven't read it, I haven't read an error, but there's no way it's correct. Like this will be a major result. It's just not within the capacities of the current models if you're reasonably well-telt-readed. And there's definitely no human has read it. Definitely the models are not able to check this kind of thing. Yeah. So, I mean,
Yeah, so this is my my expectation is that the reason it's producing short-lever things is just like that's what we can check Yeah, you can get it to produce long things that are grindy or hard to check but
Yeah, we'll have to get there. This is actually more what it says about capabilities, frontier capabilities rather than in a perhaps more negative way rather than, hey, it's just so good at these clever, no, I think that's totally fair. I mean, especially if you look at an adjacent domain like code, right? Remember reading something that cursor put out about testing their long horizon, you know, harness, in this case, we're trying to reproduce SQL light in Rust.
And it was just so telling like how far we are. And that seems like a very comparable task of like it just it's very long. You have to make sure there's something to verify that it's a correct implementation by testing a suite of cases. But you actually need a harness there in this case. It's not just like the raw models. And it takes a while and you can actually compare with different frontier versus.
you know, non frontier models who's the planner, etc. like differences in their capabilities as well. Yeah, I also think in practice like the to elicit a long proof you kind of need a harness. Yeah. And when you make a harness whose goal is to elicit a proof, I think it often decreases reliability because you're just trying to produce output. So like, ChadGPD 5.6 Pro is like very, it really tries not to say wrong stuff.
for example, and although it happens and then you'll ask it like, oh, was that correct? And it'll say no. But when you're trying to get it to ideate, you try to get it to be creative, you try to get it out of this very rigorous rush and actually get it somewhere. And I think if your interest is in, I mean, there are a lot of people who are
you know, kind of arbitrage the prestige mechanics of academic mathematics and try to elicit a lot of proofs which are not necessarily being checked. And in order to do that, I think you just decreased the reliability in order to get a lot of stuff. So, you know, I think any harness that can elicit a 250 page paper is probably not being very careful about what it's producing. And you're saying that it's decreasing or it's not reliable just because it's the capability isn't there yet. And so it's just kind of forcing a long longer horizon task on it.
Yeah, I mean in practice like how does like a human checking it like can't check a 250 page paper either like like you you know You can't reliably check it line by line What you would try to do to understand it is you try to like understand the overall global structure of the argument and you like stress test it in various ways like With this it are you mean to apply something else that I know to be false like oh like what does it work in this special case blah blah blah And also the models seem not to be able to do that kind of like more I don't know fuzzy like unit testing approved very well yet
So actually one of my favorite tests for the models, which they haven't succeeded at yet, is there's a paper, I won't name it, that came out a couple years ago that was wrong. And it was very hard to find, in close enough area to myself, that I was claiming some big result, immediately downloaded it and started reading it. And it was very hard to find the actual specific error. But it was also very clear from the structure of the argument that it couldn't work.
So it's like, you know, me and a bunch of other, he was proving something that was too strong to be true. If you can have children a little bit further. So me and a bunch of other experts like immediately like realized it was wrong and like we, you know, we emailed the author and like we kind of went back and forth until someone figured out what the precise specific error was. And so far the models seem not to have been able to do this. Like the specific error is quite subtle and they're also not able to do this kind of overall.
kind of big picture tax checking which is kind of like how people in practice check papers. Yeah, yeah, which is kind of mirrors, you know, why encode. It's like it's so clear it's good at the syntax, but you know, higher level architectural stuff, still very weak. Maybe I'll ascend there, but...
probably need some harness help. Who knows? I mean people have, you know, evolving opinions on how much the harness and the model have to co-evolve and which one is necessary, but the next model requires less. So I feel like in math it'd be very interesting to see how you, if you do any experiments with the harness there and how that improves because it is a market general reasoning. Yeah.
Yeah, I mean I do, you know, I have my own sort of bad little harness and codex. Oh yeah. But yeah, it's, but you know, I personally I do not enjoy autonomous mathematics very much. So I mostly do not use the harness. I mostly try to use it to help me understand stuff.
Okay, no, it's totally fair. Yeah, exactly. You don't want to automate your job away because that does involve you being in the loop to understand it, which is necessary to participate. Maybe to finish off, I'd love to... This could be just something you haven't thought about or actually thought a lot about. I think you also have a toddler.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So how have you... Yeah, I've been three-year-old. Yeah, three-year-old. Great. So you're one year more advanced and probably have more thoughts on this. Like, how are you thinking about... Is it her education or his education? Her. How are you thinking about her education in math and... Not to grind, but really just like how you can pass on the love of it and how to react to AI.
Yeah, so she's three. She's never used AI. She is starting to add. That's about as far as we're in. That's more for one thing right here. She can add single digit numbers, like by counting on her fingers and counting up to maybe 30 reliably and 50 semi-reliably. So I'm very proud of that. Yeah, I definitely encourage that. We talk about shapes and stuff. Actually, a couple of days ago, I woke her up and she was hiding under the blankets.
And I was like, oh, what are you up to under there, Sophia? And she was like, oh, I'm doing some math. Oh, I still did. I think you tweeted about that. That was a good word. Yeah, it was great. So I think she has some sense that I like math and she's into it because of that. Yeah, I would say I don't know. I think the world is probably going to look pretty different in 20 years or whatever. She's kind of fully adult and doing her own thing.
But you know, I think a lot of what we educate people for is like pretty robust changes in the nature of the world. Like I think the reason to learn head math has always been like to think clearly and like better understand the world. I'm like, presumably that's something you want to do, even if there are sort of extremely capable AI's.
And this is also true, you know, I personally like math a lot, but also the reason to like read a lot of books and do the humanities and so on. So I mean, I think like the actual values of the math profession and like education more broadly are like the things we definitely try to want to try to preserve that I hope to instill in my daughter. You know, how much institutions have to change to make sure that happens is maybe an open question. I think a lot.
But yeah, at least at a personal level, I'm definitely trying to convince my three-year-old that math is super cool. Oh yeah, 100%! One of her first words was, Icosihedrin. Was it what? My parents gave her a little Icosihedrin toy when she was one. That's a first word!
Yeah, not literally first word, but she learned the platonic solids quite quickly. Oh, very good. Very good. Next stop, group theory. I mean, it's like very natural. That's right, yeah. I mean, it's actually, when I teach her about addition and subtraction further, we'll do it in the context of a general group. Oh, very good. Well, at least you give the motivation. I think a lot of probably skip that part.
Yeah, yeah. And maybe this is how math grad students can also focus on training the next much younger generation to use AI in service of actually getting better at math rather than just fucking understanding. Wonderful. OK, well, thank you so much, Daniel. Thank you. It was a lot of fun. Yeah, yeah. It was a lot of fun. And yeah, I mean, I think there's going to be a lot more progress very soon. I'd love to maybe catch up and chat again. Sounds great. Thanks for listening to this episode of the A16Z podcast.
If you like this episode, be sure to like, comment, subscribe, leave us a rating or review, and share it with your friends and family. For more episodes, go to YouTube, Apple Podcasts, and Spotify. Follow us on X and A16Z, and subscribe to our substack at a16z.substack.com. Thanks again for listening, and I'll see you in the next episode. As a reminder, the content here is for informational purposes only. Should not be taken as legal business, tax, or investment advice, or be used to evaluate any investment or security,
and is not directed at any investors or potential investors in any A16Z fund. Please note that A16Z and its affiliates may also maintain investments in the companies discussed in this podcast. For more details, including a link to our investments, please see a16z.com forward slash disclosures.